INVENTORY OF THE JOHN FITCHEN PAPERS, 1927-1989
Getty Research Institute
John Fitchen papers
1927-1989
910018
Fitchen, John
4 lin. ft. (10 boxes)
Getty Research Institute Research Library Special Collections and Visual Resources 1200 Getty Center Drive, Suite 1100 Los Angeles, CA 90049-1688
American architect and architectural historian. Most of the research materials relate to three of Fitchen's books: Construction of Gothic Cathedrals, The New World Dutch Barn, and Building Construction Before Mechanization. Other papers include designs, drawings, and sketchbooks, as well as correspondence with numerous architectural historians, primarily on the subject of medieval architecture.
Administrative Information
Access
Open for use by qualified researchers.
Biographical/Historical note
John Fitchen, American architectural historian and architect, is the author of several works, among them, Construction of Gothic cathedrals (1961, 1981), New World Dutch barn (1968), and Building construction before mechanization (1986). He attended Harvard University's Graduate School of Design, where he studied with Kenneth John Conant and developed an abiding interest in medieval construction techniques.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Fitchen papers comprise research materials, manuscripts, correspondence, photographs and reviews for his publications, especially for his 3 books: Construction of Gothic cathedrals, New World Dutch barn, and Building construction before mechanization. Manuscripts and printed materials document numerous articles and lectures by Fitchen. Other files contain material for unpublished projects, including his manuscript Plot, plan and perspective. Sketches and drawings document Fitchen's designs for bookplates and buildings, including some done as a student. A sketchbook contains drawings of American Dutch barns. Correspondence with more than a dozen architectural historians centers largely on the subject of medieval architecture and construction.
The papers are arranged in 3 series: Series I. Research for major publications, ca. 1927-1986 Series II. Student work, manuscripts, lectures, drawings, ca. 1927-1989 Series III. Correspondence, ca. 1954-1984
Indexing Terms
Subjects
Fitchen, John; Ayasofya Mzesi; Harvard University. Graduate School of Design; Washington Cathedral; Architecture; Architecture, Gothic; Architecture, GothicHistory; ArchitectureHistoriography; Architecture, Medieval; Architecture, MedievalHistory; BuildingEurope; BuildingEuropeHistory; Building materialsEuropeHistory; BarnsNetherlands; BarnsUnited States; Cathedrals; CathedralsEurope; Church architecture; Church architectureEuropeHistory; Church architectureThemes, motives; Church architectureDesigns and plans; Civil engineering; Vaults (Architecture); Vaults (Architecture), Gothic
Genres and Forms of Materials
Architectural drawingsUnited States20th century; Photographs, Original; Photographic prints
Contributors
Bucher, Franois; Conant, Kenneth John, 1894-; Harvey, John Hooper; Heyman, Jacques; Horn, Walter William, 1908-; Hubka, Thomas C., 1946-; Macaulay, David; McKee, Harley J.; Placzek, Adolf K.; Szarmach, Paul E.; Van Nise, Robert L.; Wachs, William
Titles
Construction of Gothic cathedrals; New World Dutch barn; Building construction before mechanization
Container List
- Research for major publications, ca. 1954-1987, n.d., Series I.; 7 boxes
  Primarily research materials, manuscripts, correspondence, printed matter and photographs related to Fitchen's three books: The construction of Gothic cathedrals (1961, 1981), The New World Dutch barn (1968), and Building construction before mechanization (1986).
  - Gothic Cathedrals, ca. 1954-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
    - Research notes, ca. 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Drafts, 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Original drawings for ms, n.d (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with publisher, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reviews letter in response to both, 1960-1962, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gothic Cathedrals, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Manuscripts, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript, appendices, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript, notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dutch Barns, 1963-1975, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Notes draft, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript text, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence after publication, 1965-1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Papers photographs: Dutch Barns, ca. 1963-1986, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
    - Sketches. See also drawings of American barns in sketchbook, Box 9., 1963 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous photos (negatives placed in cold storage, box 10), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous plates, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Photographs for Netherlandish barns, 1982-1986, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Illustrations for manuscript, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Photo mechanicals for manuscript, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Papers photographs: Building Construction, ca. 1954-1985 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - Notes, 1954-1967 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Drafts, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript figures, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Papers photographs, ca. 1984-1987, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
    - Illustrations (n.b., post-its), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Illustrations (n.b., post-its,), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Reviews, correspondence, ca. 1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Translation, 1984-1988 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Negatives (2), pulled from Box 4, f.4, 1982-1986, n.d. (Box 10)
- Student work, manuscripts, lectures, drawings, ca. 1927-1989, Series II.; 2 boxes
  Series comprises papers related to Fitchen's publications (other than those referenced in Series I), his lectures, student work at Harvard, and drawings and designs.
  - Papers: Lectures, manuscripts, offprints, correspondence (Box 7, Folder 1-31)
    - Premier of Baseball, 1989; lecture (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - English vs. French Vaulting, 1985; lecture (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Visual Impact of the Gothic Cathedral, lecture, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Building Cheops' Pyramid, Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians (JSAH) 1978 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Early Timber Framed Construction in America, lecture, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - New World Dutch Barn, lecture, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Why Not Fountains in Winter? 1970 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Vitas, grant applications, etc; 1967-1985 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - New York State Dutch Barns, lecture, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Architecture, the Optimistic Art, AIA Journal proofs1964 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Masonry Techniques of the Middle Ages, lecture, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Untitled miscellaneous articles, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Erection of French Gothic Nave Vaults, Gazette offprint, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Plot, Plan and Perspective, manuscript, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Changing Face of the Riviera, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - An Old House of Laminated, Solid Wood Walls, Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians (JSAH) 1957 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Comment on Flying Buttresses, Gazette offprint, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Draftsman to Architect, manuscript, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Architectural Subject Matter, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Introduction to Art, manuscript, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Student drawings, Harvard, 1927-1928 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - "The Roof," manuscript (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Problem of Ventilation (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Principles of Architectural Construction (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Notes on Female Architecture (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Medieval Scaffolds (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - "Here Once Stood a House," manuscript (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - "First Book on the Moon," manuscript (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Dealing with the Inexplicable (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous designs drawings by Fitchen (Box 7, Folder 30)
      See also Box 9 for sketchbook.
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Fitchen sketchbook, n.d. (Box 9*)
    Includes measured sketches, most showing the construction of American Dutch barns.
- Correspondence, ca. 1954-1984, Series III.; 1 box
  Correspondence between Fitchen and other architectural historians, primarily dealing with the structure of medieval buildings. Letters include discussions of work in progress and critiques of publications.
  - Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 1-20)
    - James Acland, 1956-1966 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Frank Brown, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Francois Bucher, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - George Collins, 1964-1968 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Kenneth Conant, 1955-1962 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - James M. Fitch, 1956, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - John Harvey, 1954-1962 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Jacques Heyman, 1965-1971 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Walter H. Horn, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Thomas Hubka, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Lewis C. Jones, 1963-1967 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Christine Kaplan, 1977, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - David Macaulay, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Harley McKee, 1955, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Adolf Placzek, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Paul E. Szarmach, 1976, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Robert L. Van Nise, 1963-1978 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - William C. Wachs, 1962-1972 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Ben Weinreb, 1964-1971 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955-1984 (Box 8, Folder 20)